<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the Queene. Where in the Parliament holden at Westminster, in the thirteenth yeere of the Queenes Maiesties raigne, amongst other things, there was one acte and statute made, intituled an Acte against vsurie  ...</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1581-05-19</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8131.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115347</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850566</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850566</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15777</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15777)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 565:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the Queene. Where in the Parliament holden at Westminster, in the thirteenth yeere of the Queenes Maiesties raigne, amongst other things, there was one acte and statute made, intituled an Acte against vsurie  ...</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1581-05-19</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barker [i.e. B. Norton a. J. Bill], printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1581]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual printer's names and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reviving the statutes still in force.</note>
                  <note>Line 1 of text ends "thir-"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 8130 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Usury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Proclamations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15777:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the Queene.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the Parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeere of the Queenes Maieſties Raigne, amongſt other things, there was one Acte and Statute made, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled an Acte againſt vſurie, which Acte was then made to continue for, and during the ſpace of fiue yeeres next af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the end of the ſaid Parliament, and from the end of the ſaid fiue yeeres, to the end of the firſt Seſſion of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then next inſuing, as by the ſame Acte more at large it doth appeare. And foraſmuch as the ſaid fiue yeres were ended and expired in the eighteenth yeere of her Maieſties raigne, during the tune of the ſecond ſeſſion of this preſent Parliament begun at Weſtminſter in the fourteenth yeere of her Maieſties raigne, and by diuers prorogations yet continuing: therefore ſome doubts and queſtions haue bin lately moued, whether the ſaid Act &amp; Statute ſhould continue but vnto the end of the laſt Seſſion of this preſent Parliament, which in deed was the third Seſſion of the ſaid Parliament begun in the ſaid <hi>14.</hi> yere of her Maieſties raigne, and firſt holden af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ende of the ſayde fiue yeeres, or elſe vnto the end of the firſt Seſſion of the next Parliament that hereafter ſhall fortune to be newly ſummoned. Wherefore her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe conſidering that ſuch doubts and queſtions being moued and ſpread abroad, may breed ſome troubles and many inconueniences amongſt her louing Subiects, hath therefore thought good to vſe the aduiſe of her Iudges and Counſell learned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And finding plainely by their opinions that the ſaid Acte and Statute was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined or expired at the end of the ſaid laſt Seſſion of Parliament, but doeth yet ſtand in full ſtrength and force vntill the end of the firſt Seſſion of the next Parliament, which hereafter ſhall fortune to be newly ſummoned: Doeth now by the aduiſe of her Maieſties priuie Counſell for the auoiding of all troubles that by the occaſion of ſuch fryuolous queſtions might hereafter enſue, notifie and declare by this her Maieſties Proclamation, to all her louing ſubiects, that the ſaid Acte and Statute doeth and ſhall continue and remaine in ful force and effect, vntill the end of the firſt Seſſion of the next Parliament, which hereafter ſhall fortune to bee newly ſummoned. And ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and ſtraightly chargeth and commandeth all and euery her ſaid ſubiects, to accept o. it as a lawe, yet ſtanding in full force according to the good meaning thereof, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuch doubts or queſtions thereupon hereafter to be had, made, or moued by any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, in any of her Highneſſe courts of Record or els where.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at her Maieſties Pallace of Weſtminſter <date>the nineteenth day of May. In the xxiii. yeere of her Highneſſe Raigne.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
